A Guide to the Papers of the Brockenbrough, Lamb, Fauntleroy and Smith families, 1835-1945
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Brockenbrough, Lamb, Fauntleroy and Smith families, 1835-1945
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10987-a
This collection consists of (ca.) 1500 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was deposited by James C. Lamb, III on 1990 Nov 12.
Biographical/Historical Information
Virginia family residing at "Belle Ville," Warsaw, Richmond County and in Tappahannock, Essex County.
Scope and Content Information
This collection, ca. 1835-1945, of ca. 1500 items, consists primarily of family papers of the Brockenbrough and Lamb families of the farm known as "Belle Ville" in Warsaw, Richmond County, in the Northern Neck area of Virginia. The collection is organized in the following series: Correspondence; Financial Papers and Receipts; Legal Papers; Topical and Miscellaneous; Ledgers; Photographs and Scrapbooks; Oversize Items; and Oversize bound volumes. Of special interest are slave lists, letters from soldiers in World War I, photographs of Charlottesville and the University of Virginia, and a letter describing Egypt and the Middle East in the 1870s.
The bulk of the collection concerns members of the Brockenbrough and Lamb families belonging to the branch charted here:
William Fauntleroy Brockenbrough (1826-1890) m. Eliza Bland Smith
Their issue:
Saide Smith B. (1862-1949)
Alice Waller (Sis Allie) B. (1870-1955)
Agnes Atkinson B. (1876-1967)
Eliza Bland (Lila) B. (1877-1917)
Saide Smith B. m. 1885 James Christian Lamb, brother of John Lamb (1840-1924)
Their issue:
William Brockenbrough L. (1886-?)
James Christian L. Jr. (1891-1943)
Eliza Bland L. (1898-?)
Other members of the family (figuring primarily in the ledgers) are Austin Brockenbrough, William Fauntleroy, and Lucy Yates Gray (nee Brockenbrough). Both the Smith and Brockenbrough families appear to have been planters until fairly late in the nineteenth century, according to the ledgers, letters, and legal papers of this collection. James C. Lamb, Sr. was a circuit court judge in Richmond; his elder son W. Brockenbrough Lamb was also a lawyer and judge; and his younger son, James Jr., was an engineer and served in the first World War. John Lamb was a member of the House of Representatives, chairing the Committee on Agriculture in the 62nd Congress, and served in the Confederate army (Company D, Third Virginia Cavalry).
The correspondence is arranged by recipient. Of special interest are letters from various men during their service in France during World War I. The letters describe the day-to-day life of soldiering, troop movements, conditions on ships making the Atlantic crossing, and (most fully) the country and people of France after the end of the war. The letters were sent to Eliza Bland Lamb by Frank Brown, Gilbert Campbell, Hollyday Compton, James C. Lamb, Jr., J. Warren Quackenbush, Ernest Turner, and others in the miscellaneous file, and to Saide Lamb by James, C. Lamb, Jr.. In addition, in the miscellaneous correspondence folder there is a letter dated April 4, 1873, to "My dear Mother" (Mrs. D.R. Hagner) from Julian Howard, nephew of W.F. Brockenbrough; the letter was written in Alexandria, Egypt, and goes into some detail in describing the pyramids and travel to various sites in the Middle East.
The majority of the financial papers are notes and minor correspondence relating to personal financial matters of the members of the Brockenbrough and Lamb families and to the business of their farms. The receipts record mercantile and farm-produce transactions, and have been sorted chronologically by decade. The legal papers contain bonds, insurance papers, estate settlements, real estate transactions, and legal agreements. There is a folder for papers relating to the management and sale of the farm known as "Bay Quarter," formerly a part of "Belle Ville," and another on the Tappahannock Ferry and its parent company.
Among the topical and miscellaneous papers there is a folder of World War I newspapers published by the American Expeditionary Forces, a folder of miscellaneous printed material, and two items in oversize folders: a certificate from the Nurses' Board of Examiners licensing Eliza Bland Brockenbrough to practice nursing in the state of Virginia, and two copies of a floor plan drawing for alterations to the second floor of "Old School, Warsaw, Virginia." There are cancelled checks, school records, a birth, marriage and death register torn from a Brockenbrough family Bible, a plan for lots in Belle Ville Heights, a copy of an order from R.E. Lee, poems and essays, and a Bank of the Commonwealth Stock Certificate.
There are twenty-six bound volumes boxed with the collection and three oversize volumes. The box listing below details the contents of each of these volumes, which include photograph scrapbooks, school notebooks, diaries, accounts, and ledgers.
Contents List
- Correspondence
  - Letters to Alice Brockenbrough 1899-1917, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Letters to Agnes Brockenbrough 1896-1911 (Box 1)
  - Letters to Eliza Bland Brockenbrough 1891-1913, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence of Eliza Bland Brockenbrough and James C. Lamb, Sr. 1884-1901, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Letters to the Misses Brockenbrough 1904-1916, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Letters to William Fauntleroy Brockenbrough 1879-1898, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Letters of Frank Brown to Eliza Bland Lamb 1918 (Box 1)
  - Letters of Gilbert Campbell to Eliza Bland Lamb 1917-1918 (Box 1)
  - Letters of Hollyday Compton to Eliza Bland Lamb 1917-1918 (Box 1)
  - Letters of J.H. Graves to Eliza Bland Lamb 1915-1918 (Box 1)
  - Letters of J.P. Wetherill to Eliza Bland Lamb 1918-1919 (Box 2)
  - Letters of Asbury Kern to Eliza Bland Lamb 1908-1927 (Box 2)
  - Letters of Brockenbrough Lamb to Eliza Bland Lamb 1909-1918 (Box 2)
  - Letters of James Christian Lamb, Jr., to Eliza Bland Lamb 1906-1920, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Letters of John Lamb to Eliza Bland Lamb 1906-1909 (Box 2)
  - Letters of Tayloe Murphy to Eliza Bland Lamb 1917-1918 (Box 2)
  - Letters of Olaf A[rnesen?] to Eliza Bland Lamb 1915-1916 (Box 3)
  - Letters of J. Warren Quackenbush to Eliza Bland Lamb 1916-1918 (Box 3)
  - Letters of Ernest Turner to Eliza Bland Lamb 1914-1919,1941,n.d. (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Letters to Eliza Bland Lamb 1904-1918 (Box 3)
  - Letters to James C. Lamb, Jr. 1905-1911,n.d. (Box 3)
  - Letters to James C. Lamb, Sr. 1900-1901 (Box 3)
  - Letters to Saide Lamb Letters to Saide Lamb (Box 3)
  - Letters of James C. Lamb, Jr. to Saide Lamb 190[6]-1919,n.d. (Box 4)
  - Letters to William Brockenbrough Lamb 1897-1908 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1867-1947,n.d. (Box 4)
  - Letters of Condolence 1905,1917, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Invitations 1905-1917 (Box 4)
- Financial Papers
  - Financial Records and Correspondence 1849-1905,n.d., 7 folders (Box 5)
  - Receipts 1850-1909, 6 folders (Box 5)
  - Receipts 1910-1939, 3 folders (Box 6)
- Legal Papers
  - Legal Papers re "Bay Quarter" 1897-1899 (Box 6)
  - Legal Papers re Tappahannock Ferry 1899-1901,1907 (Box 6)
  - Legal Papers 1844-1889, 4 folders (Box 6)
  - Legal Papers 1890-1919, n.d., 4 folders (Box 7)
- Topical and Miscellaneous
  - Bank of the Commonwealth Stock Certificate 1860 (Box 7)
  - Birth, Marriage and Death Register torn from Brockenbrough Bible n.d. (Box 7)
  - Blueprints for second floor plan alterations to Old School at Belle Ville 1929 (Oversize M-19)
  - Cancelled Checks ca. 1890-1920 (Box 7)
  - Composite Photograph of Lambda Chapter, University of Virginia, of Kappa Alpha Fraternity 1878-1880 (Oversize M-19)
  - General Order 26, By Command of Gen. Robert E. Lee 1864 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous n.d. (Box 7)
  - Nurses' Board of Examiners Certificate for Eliza Bland Brockenbrough 1905 (Oversize M-19)
  - Overruled Cases, Some Notes on the New Code of Virginia, by James C. Lamb 1889 (Box 7)
  - Photograph of the Alumni Pageant for the University of Virginia held at the Colonnades on June 15, 1914 1914 (Oversize 25)
  - Plan for Lots in "Belle Ville Heights" 1941 Sep 9 (Box 7)
  - Poems and Essays n.d. (Box 7)
  - Recipes and Knitting Instructions n.d. (Box 7)
  - Report Cards 1876(1900-1901)1911 (Box 7)
- Bound Volumes
  A through E are Eliza Bland Lamb's school notebooks.
  - Textiles (Box 8)
  - Architecture (Box 8)
  - Theory of Cooking (Box 8)
  - Sanitation (Box 8)
  - English (Box 8)
  - Recipe Book (Box 8)
  - Eliza Bland Lamb Scrapbook (Box 9)
  - Eliza Bland Lamb Honeymoon Journal (as Mrs. E.B. Griffith) (Box 9)
  - Receipt Book of Vincent Shackleford, Sheriff of Richmond County, Virginia, 1817 (Box 9)
  - 1867 Diary of William F. Brockenbrough (used for accounts) (Box 9)
  - Mr. Smith's Negroes and Farm Ledger (Box 9)
  - William F. Brockenbrough Account Book 1852-1881 (Box 9)
  - Willoughby N. Smith "Summerfield" Account Book, with Negroes inherited from his father, James M. Smith, 1863-1881 (Box 9)
  - W.F. Brockenbrough Farm Notebook, 1876 (Box 9)
  - James C. Lamb Jr. Expense Notebook (Juvenilia) (Box 9)
  - Photograph Scrapbook: Family, U.Va., V.M.I., launching of USS Pennsylvania (March 16, 1915), Tappahannock Ferry, Belle Ville, Washington, D.C. (Box 9)
  - Photograph Scrapbook: U.Va., Newport News, Richmond (Box 10)
  - Photograph Scrapbook: Rappahannock River canoe trip, river scenes, family picnic (Box 10)
  - Photograph Scrapbook: Belle Ville, U.Va., sailing trip, farm & animals, Charlottesville Woolen Mills, duck hunting (Box 10)
  - Tuition Account Ledger for private school run by Lucy Y. Gray, 1854-1862 (Box 10)
  - S.D. Edwards Index and accounts for a [trucking] firm, 1940s (Box 11)
  - W.F. Brockenbrough Farm Ledger, 1861-1886 (Box 11)
  - Ledger, mostly empty, 1855-1856 (Box 11)
  - Ledger re estates of Austin and John F. Brockenbrough (Box 11)
  - French Lessons, estate accounts 1859-1861 (Box 11)
  - Estates of Austin Brockenbrough and Lucy Y. Gray, with Slave records of each, ca. 1870, 1877 (Box 11)
  - Medical Ledger and Estate accounts of Austin Brockenbrough 1856-1859 (Oversize 1)
  - "Journal #2"; General Store Accounts, Tappahannock, Virginia 1843-1858 (Oversize 2)
  - "Ledger #1"; Merchandise Sold Accounts, Tappahannock, Virginia 1851-1853 (Oversize 3)
  - World War I Newspapers 1917-1918 (Box 12)
  - Newspaper Clippings 1900, n.d. (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Materials n.d. (Box 12)